welcome to another GrandMA3 tutorial
this time we're going to talk about
selection grid and a MAtricks. Selection grid and
MAtricks are two different things but they are
kind of connected i mean you can use both without
using the other but but working with them together
is extremely powerful and i'm gonna show you why
it's really powerful in this tutorial so if you
are interested in selection grid and MAtricks this
is definitely the tutorial for you so let's start
in our view here with our layout default view we
don't need that we can close it down and we can
open our selection grid we can scale it a little
bit down like this we can open our layout view
over here if i can find it there we go we can put
it all the way up here and we can open our MAtricks
down here so this is the view we need let's let's
have a look at our screen right now i have my
selection grid up here you can open that window i
have my layout view over here so we can see what's
going on and i have my MAtricks down here so let's
start with our selection grid. Our selection grid
is a representation of our fixtures in x y and z
space you can turn on x y and z down here in your
MAtricks window and you can scroll down and say
okay this is our y-axis this is our z-axis and
this is our x-axis in this tutorial we are only
going to work on the x-axis so if we close these
ones down then they disappear then they're not
going to clutter our view here up here we have our
selection grid and if i choose a range of fixtures
it's going to open up in our selection grid and
now we can use our MAtricks to manipulate whatever
is going on up here so if i press this one the x
it's basically the same thing as pressing next on
your on your console or on your on your keyboard
right now i'm just using my keyboard and i can go
back and forth so that's fine if i want to have
some blocks i can say i have two blocks and
if you look at our layout view over here now
and you have to open the layout view too to see
exactly what's going on now it's choosing blocks
of two every time i am moving one step forward and
again if i want blocks of three blocks of four and
basically this means that if i apply an effect or
a color or whatever it's gonna do it on all those
four simultaneously so if i go back again block
and then go down to group then i can group them in
groups of two groups of three four five six
and say for instance we let's just clear this
and say we wanna select this one up here and we
wanna select all our washes then you can see we
have all 24 fixtures selected like this but if
i use my group and press next i can simply say i
want them in groups of 12 then it's going to take
the first ones of of each fixture type so it's
basically going to say okay i have 24 fixtures
but i choose fixture number one and then i skip
the next 11 and then i take the next one skip the
next 11 and so on and so forth so basically that's
how grouping works let's just reset grouping
again down to nothing and then say wings what
are wings wings are basically you choose the first
and the last one in a selection with a group of
or with with wings of two so if you see here it
shows the first one and it shows the last one
which is fine if you have a group if we
clear this and say i just want to choose
these ones up here and then i apply wings of
2 and when i press next it's going to take
number 1 and number 12 and then all the way
towards the center and this is the way it works
but there's another way we can we can do
this with using our grid layout let's just uh
go in and off everything here let's take
our master cue list down there we go
if i choose all my profile spots like
this and then i choose all my auras
then they come in after each other i can take
another tool which is new i believe to the
Grand MA 3 and set a width of 1 which
selects all of them at once the next one
divides it into two groups into three
four five six seven so on and so forth
and if i go all the way up to 12 like this
then it's going to select the first one
let's just reset that one and go all the way up to
this one then it's gonna select the first one in
in the row the next one in the row and so
on so this is uh how grid is really powerful
and again if we take all our profile spots we
select them where the blue square is this is where
it's going to place the next selected fixture so
basically if i put the next selected fixture down
here and i choose this range it's going to come
right underneath it and again i can do it with
i need to put it down here i can do it with all
our dimmers and then i can say okay i have all my
atomics here i only have six atomics but i have
12 of every other fixture so i can just place my
blue cursor and then skip one select the fixture
skip one select the fixture skip two and select it
and then i suddenly have a different layout and
if i have this layout and apply an effect and i
apply an effect to it then it's gonna see all this
as basically one fixture of one um one selection
so if i go into my dimmer for instance and say at
zero then i choose the next step here we go zero
then i choose my next step i set that to a hundred
and then it's gonna start oscillating between
zero and one hundred if i go in and apply a
phase to that 0 through 360 for instance
you see it's going to follow it's going to follow
the selection so basically it's going to say
all in the first selection here is treated
as one fixture it's going to apply the same
dimmer effect to it and the next one and so
forth and if we go into the phaser and set
another way of looking at it then it's going to
be like this this would be a little bit difficult
to do it's not impossible but it's going to be
a little bit difficult to do on GrandMA 2
because you need to calculate some you have
to have some dummy fixtures in between here or
something like that to to make sure
that it selects it in in the right order
but here it's very very easy to set up your
your selection or your grid or your fixtures
in the selection grid and then you
can actually store it so if i say
store right now oh that was the select
button that was the add button here we go
if i say store to this right here and i clear
when i select the group next time it already
has this fixture selection so now you
can change the fixture selection around
as much as you want you also have the shuffle over
here so once again if we select all our fixtures
like this maybe we put it into the group selection
we already had let's once again start an effect we
say zero on step one we say 100 on step two it
starts to oscillate then if i shuffle down here
like this and apply a face to it it's 0
through 360 again sorry and then i shuffle it
then you can see it's going to shuffle and every
time i push the shuffle here it's going to choose
a different randomization of the fixtures and i
think you can actually see it if you zoom in here
704, 304, 110, and so on so basically it just moves
everything around so you can do really complex
things and that's the the shuffle up here so
there's a lot of interesting things in the
the new selection grid combined with the MAtricks
so play with it and learn how it works i mean it's
quite simple to work with as soon as you get
your head around it for the first time you have
to see a few tutorials and and then it actually
starts to make sense but it's a pretty cool tool
if you enjoyed this video please give it a
like and maybe even subscribe to the channel
and that way you get a notification next
time we upload a video so i hope you get
something out of this and if you have any
questions please leave a comment down below
and i will try to answer them as good
as i can see you next time bye bye